<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The olde fayth of greate Brittaygne, and the newe learnynge of Inglande wherunto is added a symple instruction, concernynge the Kinges Maiesties procedinges in the co[m]munyon. Compyled by R.V.</title>
            <author>R. V., fl. 1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 157:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The olde fayth of greate Brittaygne, and the newe learnynge of Inglande wherunto is added a symple instruction, concernynge the Kinges Maiesties procedinges in the co[m]munyon. Compyled by R.V.</title>
                  <author>R. V., fl. 1549.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker. dwellynge in the Sauoy rentes wythoute Temple-barre. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendu[m] solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1549?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-b c⁴.</note>
                  <note>"A simple instruction concernynge the Kinges maiesties procedinges in the communion" has separate divisional title; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19623:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19623:1"/>
            <p> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The olde Fayth of greate Brittaygne / and the newe learnynge of Inglande, Wherunto is added a ſymple in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, concernynge the Kinges Maieſties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinges in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munyon. Compyled by R. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Nume. xvj. ⁋</bibl>
               <p>In this ye ſhall knowe that the lorde hath ſent me / for to do all thoſe thinges whyche ye ſee, and that I haue not inuented them of myne owne harte.</p> 
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at London by Anthony Scoloker. Dwellynge in the Sauoy rentes Wythoute Temple-barre.</p>
            <p>Cum Priuilegio ad Imprimendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:19623:2"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:2"/> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Euangeliſt, Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Witneſſeth, that Chryſte ſayd: all power is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me in heauen and earth. Go therfore &amp; teach al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Baptiſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the holyghoſt, teaching them to obſerue all thynges what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer I commaunded you. Theys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des therfore (go teach all nacions) may pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the woorde of God to haue bene taught here in this Realme euen in the tyme of the Apoſtles and diſcyples of Chryſt: for then this realme was tributory or payd tribute to the Romaynes, and in eſtimaiton wyth them. And for a farther profe, Eulebius in his Eccleſiaſticall hyſtory, the thyrd booke and fyrſt chapter / ſayth: the Iewes beyng perſecuted wyth all euels, the apoſtles and diſciples of our ſauiour departed to go prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che by all partes of the worlde. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the great Chronicle of lytle brytaygne, recyteth, that Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llus, ſonne of Maruis / was king in thys realme after hys father. Who in hys yonge age was brought vp in Rome. And for ſo muche as he knewe the maners of the Romaynes, he had them all his lyfe in honoure, and payd them ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elys
<pb facs="tcp:19623:3"/> tribute. For he ſawe the whole worlde try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butours to htem. He had the prynces and the nobylytye of hys realme in greate reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and many tymes ſhewed great lybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralytie, in geuing them gyftes &amp; preſentes: And alſo vnto thoſe whyche lyued vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly: and for this cauſe was he ſo beloued of all folkes, that, after hys death, they cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to wepe. He reygned longe and left a ſonne called Lucius whyche was kynge after hys father. In whoſe tyme (as the ſame chronicle recyteth) was a great nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of Chryſtyans baptyſed, whych open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached the goſpell of oure ſauyour and Redemer Ieſus Chryſt. Who Kyng Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius gladlye hearde / and he, beynge in ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holyghoſt, had a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre to be chryſtened, and for to obteyne the ſame / ſent meſſengers to Elether / then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge Byſſhop of Rome, for lerned menne / Who ſent hym twoo Famous menne, one called Faganus, and the other Damianus.</p>
            <p>Who alſo at ther commynge / preached before Kynge Lucius / the whole lyfe and lawe of oure ſauyour and redemer Ieſus Chryſte. At whoſe preachynge, the Kynge wythe hys whole houſholde was Chryſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the yere of Chryſt. 185. And vnder y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:3"/> fayth or belefe of one only god, were edified diuers Temples. And thus we ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte fayth receued in thys Realme to be taught accordyng to the Goſpell. For at that tyme were fewe Ceremonyes vſed amonge the Chryſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, other then were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the goſpell. And thys pure &amp; ſyncere fayth con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynued among the Brytaynes in thys Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme tyll the yere of Chriſt. 544. In which tyme (as Ranolph of Chiſter recyteth in the .v. boke the. 9 chapter of Polichronica) Ethelbert was kyng ouer kent. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Auſten the monke came from Rome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for, then beyng byſſhop of Rome Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory the great. Whiche Auſten at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, rayſed vp a banner of the Croſſe / &amp; ſhewed a Table that he brought, wheron was paynted a crucyfyx, and ſong the Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes Letany / and ſayd maſſe, which the kig wolde not receaue at the fyrſt. But ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, Auſten perſuaded the king a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hys people after ſuche a ſorte / that he receaued Auſtens ware. And Gregory his maſter / hearing of this, ſent Auſten more helpers. and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, ſent bokes &amp; reliques of holy ſaits: and thus was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> new lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g brought ito this reame of w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> we ſe much yet remay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng in the church / at this preſent daye / al
<pb facs="tcp:19623:4"/> the Britaynes at that time, wolde in no wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe receaue, as apeareth in the ſame. ix chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Whervppon Auſten called a counſel of vij. Brityſh byſſhoppes, and of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mous monkes of Bangorin wales. Who, at their comming to the counſell, an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite meting with them. demaunded whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were going? and they anſwered / to Auſtens counſel. Then ſayd the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myte to them. When ye come there, if Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten ryſe and mete wyth you lyke a meke Dyſciple of Chriſte, then receaue his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. If not, returne agayne. Which they did, in that Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhewed not him ſelfe me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke, wherat Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was diſpleaſed and ſayd vnto them. Conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to me in thre thinges / if ye wyll not agree to the reſt. That is ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe Eaſter in dewe tyme, and Chriſten af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner of the church of Rome, and preache Gods worde to the Inglyſh. But they wold not conſent to him. Whervppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made them anſwere, ſaying: he was warned by inſpyracyon, that they whiche wolde not receaue peace of theyr brethern / ſhulde of hym receaue warre and wrath. Which he brought to paſſe. For he cauſed Ethelbertus kyng of Northumberla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a .ij. M. L. mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes of Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gor, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> lyued by
<pb facs="tcp:19623:4"/> the ſweate of theyr browes, hauing nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> syeſe how this new fayth was brought into this realme. 409. yeares after the fyrſt. And howe in the fyrſt was preached the whole lyfe and law of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour &amp; Redeamer Ieſus Chriſt. And in the laſt, wyth bloude, was ſet vp a banner, a crucifix, the popes Letany, and Maſſes, with bokes and relykes of holye ſaynctes / Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denieth not, that the Britaynes kept eaſter, and Chriſtened, but it was after the inſtitucion of the apoſtles, and not after y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vſe of the Romaynes (whiche Crucyfyed Chryſton good frydaye, &amp; rayſed hi vp on eaſterday) y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Romaynes vſed in theyr chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtening, oyle, creame, ſalt and ſpyttie, as we ſee at theſe dayes. Which vſage / in thoſe dayes / the Brytaynes wolde not receaue. Foganus and Damianus taught the Bry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynes to buylde diuers Temples vnder y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fayth of one only God. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taught to buyld churches of peter and of paule. And ſence hys ſucceſſours haue taught to build churches of Auſten, Dunſtone / Ancelme / Blaſy and Thomas becket. So that we may ſee, that by theſe meanes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pure and ſiynceare trueth hath bene darkened. Full wel might Peter ſay, there ſhalbe falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="tcp:19623:5"/> among you. 2. Petri. 1. Which pryue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſhall bring in dampnable ſectes, denying y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde that bought them. I pray you, Is not the popiſh prieſthod a dampnable ſect / whiche ſaye / they can make theyr maker in their maſſes, and offer him vp for a ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, whiche preuayleth the quicke and dead? Peter myght well ſay / that all ſuch ſhuld bryng vnto them ſelues ſwift dampnaty o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and that many ſhuld follow their dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble wayes 'by which the way of truth ſhal be euell ſpoken of. How ſay you (O ye po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſh biſſhops a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d prieſtes which maynteyn Auſtens dampnable Ceremonyes) do ye not cauſe the way of truth, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, to be euell ſpoken of? Axe ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in dennes and corners to ſaye, and heare maſſes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d take holybread, and holy water / with ſuch lyke / and they wyll ſpeake euell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell / ſaying, it was neuer mery ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce it was preached. Therfore, leaſte ye brig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwyft dampnacion vppon you, leaue Bala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ams marke, and confeſſe wyth Peterthat ye haue denied Chryſt / and alſo that wyth Paule ye haue perſecuted Chryſte / and be no more aſhamed to returne vnto Chryſt, then was Peter and Paule. For truly ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loug as ye ſay Maſſe and lyfte the breade
<pb facs="tcp:19623:5"/> and wyne aboue your heades / geuynge the peple to vnderſtande your maſſe to be vayl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lable for quycke and deade. Ye denyethe lord that bought you, and ſerue not Chryſt, but Antychriſt / as wytneſſeth. ſ. Barnarde in his .xxxiij. ſermon vppon the cantycles / ſaying: they are the miniſters of Chryſt &amp; ſerue antichryſt. They walke (ſayth he) in the honours of the goodes of the Lord, to the which lord, they do no honour:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce (ſayth he) commeth the be wty of the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lot, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> thou ſeeſt dayly decked like pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yers. And farther, he being aſhamed with the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetouſnes and pryde whiche then reygned and yetreygneth amonge you, ſayth vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .ix. pſal me. Almooſt all Chriſtians ſeks theyr owne proffyt, and not that of Ieſus Chryſt. And haue altered the offices of the Eccleſiaſticall dignitie to vnſhamefull gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and workes of darkenes. In theſe thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges (ſaythe he) is not ſought the health of ſoules / but the voluptuouſnes of Ryches. And herefore are y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> i ſhaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, herefor freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they the churches, celebratyng maſtes and ſyngyng pſalmes. Thus ye ſe howe the forefathers abhorred theſe thyngs whych reygne yet at thysdaye. Therfore let the Maſſe go agayne to Rome, wyth all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens
<pb facs="tcp:19623:6"/> trynkets and cleaue to the lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, in the w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is declared howe that Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte offered his body for vs, and ſhedde hys bloude for the remyſſion of our ſynnes / as heceafter ſhalbe declared, after the mynde of the Auncient doctours: whiche ye maye perceaue / is conformable to the ſcripturs, where as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> aduerſaryes haue not the doe tryne, which is agreable wyth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, but fayned fantaſyes and Auncient cuſtumes, which the apoſtles abhorred. And therfore Peter bad vs remember the wordes whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che were told vs before of the holy prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and alſo the commaundementes of vs (ſayth he) that be apoſtles of the lorde and Sauyour .ij. Petri. iij. And Chryſte ſayd Luke the .x. He that heareth you, hereth me and he that deſpyſeth you, deſpyſeth me. And he that deſpyſeth me, deſpiſeth hym that ſent me. Wherfore let vs not deſpyſe Chryſt and his apoſtles leaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges which fell vppon the Iewes for theyr ingratitude, fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs. Wherof the lorde defende vs. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="half_title">
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:6"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:7"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:7"/>
               <head>A Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Inſtruction concernynge the Kinges maieſties procedinges in the communion.</head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Numer. xvi.</bibl>
                  <p>In thys ye ſhall know that the lorde hath ſent me for to do all thoſe thynges which ye ſee / and that I haue not inuented them of myne owne harte.</p> 
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="body_of_part">
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:8"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:19623:8"/>
               <head>A Symple inſtruction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſties procedinges in the Communion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entell Reader / It is not vnknowen what an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ſclaunder dyuers haue taken, in that the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges Maieſtie wyth hys honourable Counſel, hath gone about to alter or take away the abuſe of the communion, vſed in the Maſſe, both contrarye to Chryſtes inſtytucion and the miniſtracion of the Apoſtles and catholyke fathers in the prymatiue Church. And for ſo muche as the, ſame abuſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion hath been many yeares in eſtimacion, and counted holy: the ignoraunt and vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (for lacke of Godly inſtruction) eſteme the ſame abuſe called the Maſſe, to be the principall poynt of Chryſtianitie, to whom the alteryng therof apeareth very ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. But if ſuch parſones, to whom it apeareth ſtraunge, wolde but ponder and way, how our forefathers haue been robbed, and the common welth decayed through the abuſe of the Maſſe / they ſhuld ſone perceaue the
<pb facs="tcp:19623:9"/> dyfference betwene the communion and it. And that the kynges maieſtie and hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable counſell, doth but as they becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by Gods worde. Conſyderynge that Saules Kyngdome was taken from hym for euer / for that he diſobeyed Gods worde. And agayne / callyng to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great &amp; manyfold vyctoryes / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> God gaue to ſuch kinges and rulers as obeyed hys worde, wyth the dyſcommendacyons of the euell, and the commendacions of the good, as appeareth in the .vi. laſte chapters of Eccleſiaſticus. Amonge which / Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the. 48. chapter / is commended after thys ſorte. For Ezechias had done the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that pleaſed the lorde / and remayned ſted faſtlye in the waye of Dauid hys Father. Nowe Ezechias brake downe the braſen ſerpent / which Moyſes / as apeareth Nu mer. 21. Set vp for a token. 700. yeares a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d odde, before the commyng of Ezechias / the which the prieſtes of the Iſraelites after the death of Moyſes / abuſed, and gaue it a new name / and called it Nehuſthan, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as our popiſh prieſtes ſtyl do abuſe the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſupper or communion / callynge it ſtyll a new name: Miſſa or Maſſe. But what dyd Ezechias after he ſawe the abuſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19623:9"/> the braſen ſerpent? Dyd he regarde mans doctrine, or the auncient cuſtome / becauſe it had bene abuſed .vij. C. years? No forſoth, he regarded none of theſe thynges. But the ſcrypture / Reg. iiij. the .xviij. chapter, ſayth he brake down the braſen Serpent whych moyſes had made. For vnto that tyme, had the chyldren of Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll brenty incenſe vnto it / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d called it Nehuſthan. Wherfore deare Reader / maruell not at the Kynges Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyes procedynges, ſo longe as he hath the ſcrypture for hym. And loke that thou ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d eſchue the procedinges of the pope and his ſworne ſoldiers / whych are wholy agaynſt God and hys word: as are: Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſters / Smythes
/ Perynes &amp; other lyke, By whoſe bookes thow mayeſt playnnelye parceaue them to flee from the ſcryptures. Maynteynynge ſuperſtycyon and falſe fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned relygion. Yea, euen the maſſe Whych is a derogation to chryſtes bloud. For Chryſt left the Sacrament of hys body and bloud, in bread and wyne to be eaten and dronken in the remembraunce of hys death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and not to be loked at, as the Iſraely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes dyd at the braſen ſerpent. For the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent was ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppe for a token of Chryſtes paſſion, then to come, which the Iſraelites
<pb facs="tcp:19623:10"/> loked for as witneſſeth. S. John in the. 4 chapt. ſaying: As Moiſes lyft vp the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in the wyldernes, euen ſo muſt the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne of man be lift vp / that who ſoeuer bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth in him, ſhal not peryſh, but haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. Thus, euen as the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was a fygure of Chryſtes paſſion, then to come, as witneſſeth Moyſes / Deutere. xviij. ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing. And the lorde ſayd vnto me, they haue well ſpoken, I wyll rayſe them vp a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet from among theyr brethern, lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the, &amp; will put my wordes in his mouth and he ſhall ſpeake vnto them all that I ſhall commaund him / and who ſoeuer wyl not harken to my woordes whiche he ſhall ſpeake in my name, of hym wyll I require it. O ye papiſtes, why wyll ye not harken to the wordes of Chryſt the great prophet which he ſpake of his communion, in Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew, Marke and Luke? And alſo to the miniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Paul. 1. Cor. 11. Who ſayth, as often as ye eate thys bread, and drynke thys cuppe, ye ſhall ſhew the lordes death tyll he come. Here we ſe, howe in eatyng and drinki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, through fayth, is declared vn to vs, how that Chryſt offered his bodye, and ſhedde hys Bloude vppon the Croſſe, for the Remyſſyon of Synnes, ones for
<pb facs="tcp:19623:10"/> all. Paule ſayth not, as often as the pryeſt lyfteth the breade and wyne aboue his ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen crowne, for the Papyſts to gale at, ye ſhall ſhew the lordes death tyll he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om, but he ſayth, as often as ye eate of thys breade, and drinke of this cuppe / ye ſhall ſhew the lordes death tyll he come. And thys is alſo the mynde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient catholyk fathers, to receaue it as a memoryall of hys death, and not to eate it thinkyng or beleuing him to be there ryallye, as he was borne of the virgin mary.</p>
               <p>For. Sayncte Auſten in hys Booke intituled the chriſtian diuinitie, alleagynge the fyrſte Epyſtle and the fyrſte chapter of Paule to Timot. He is (ſayth he) immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall, for ſo much as he can not dy. But ouer all where as the ſcripture of the one parte and of the other / in the canonicall bokes ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth furth the mouing of the ſoule in God tyther the humayne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres / that is to ſay the head, the eares, the eyes and other lyke / they ought not to be vnderſtande carnally, after the ſtorye, as they are vnderſtande of the Iewes, and diuerſe other heretikes ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uouryng carnally, which eſteme God to be corporall and locall. But all thinges ought
<pb facs="tcp:19623:11"/> ſpiritually vnderſtande and confeſſed of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>If any beleue that in God are humayne Members eyther mouynge of the Soul: without doubte, he forgeth ydolles in hys harte. Item. ſ. Bedain hys recolectyon, &amp; alſo. S. Auſten in his ſermon made to the people at the communyon. My brethren (ſaye they) Herefore are theſe thynges cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sacramentes / for ſo muche as in them there is one thynge ſeem and an other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. That which is ſene, is a corporall thynge / But that thynge whych is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, hath a ſpyrytuall frute. The ſayd Auſten in his .xxx. treatiſe vpon. S. Iohn ſayth: The body of Chryſte is ryſen from death, and muſt be in one place. Alſo in hys boke agaynſt Adamantum, the xij Chapter ſayth: theſe thre thynges: The bloude ys ſprete. This is my body, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſtone was Chryſte / He teacheth theſe thynges to be ſpoken as though he ſpake by a fygure in Signe and ſygnyfiynge and amonge other thynges, ſayth theſe woordes: I maye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound thys commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be a token, for the lord doubted not to ſaye, thys is my body, when he gaue the ſigne of his body / Also SAYNCTE Ambroſe vpon the fyrſte Epyſtell, the Aleauenth Chappyter
<pb facs="tcp:19623:11"/> to the Corinthians ſayeth. In ſo much as we are delyuered by the death of the lorde / hauing remembraunce of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in eating and drinking ſignifieth the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and bloude whyche hathe been offered for vs. Alſo. S. Ciprianin the ſeconde bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of hys Epyſtle, the iij. chapter, ſayth: for ſo much as in al ſacrifices we make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the paſſion of Chriſt. For the lordes paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice that we offer. We ought not to do otherwyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done. For the ſcripture ſayth as often as ye eate this breade, and drynke this chalyce, ye anounce or declare the death of Chriſt tyll he come.</p>
               <p>Then as often as we offer the chalyce in the remembraunce of the lorde and of hys paſſion: we do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which apeareth to haue been done of the lorde. Good Reader, here haue ye ſufficient Aucthours both of the ſcryptures and alſo of the Catholyke doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures: agaynſte the tranſubſtancyon and the abuſe of the maſſe: whych: if God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt: ye maye ſee no leſſe abuſed: then was y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> braſen ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. for euen as the wicked prye ſtes of the Iſraelytes ſenced the braſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent geuyng it a new name callyng it Nehu ſthan: geuyng the ISRAELYTS to
<pb facs="tcp:19623:12"/> vnderſtande that by it / they receaued theyr health. Euen ſo hath the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe and papyſtes inuented the tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation in our kynde, geuing the Chriſtya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to vnderſtand that CHRIST is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that kynde which is hanged ouer the alter, euen as he was borne of hys Bleſſed mother the virgyn mary. And therfore do the papiſtes knele to it, put of theyr cappes to it, knock theyr breſtes befor it / and their prieſtes ſence it. But trulye aſſured I am that the popiſh pryeſtes haue euen ſo good ſcriptures to proue this, as the Iſraelites had to proue theyr Nehuſthan. Wherfore let no man murmer agaynſt the Kynges maieſties procedinges. For his grace hath the ſcryptures for hym / where the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes haue none. And that maye be well gathered by theyr ſeking of inſurrections / and in ſtyrring the ſcottes and frenchmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agaynſt the Kynges maieſtie. Thys is no new, but an Aunciynt Practyſe of theyrs, as ye may well perceaue in Tindals prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe of prelates. But by Gods helpe, his grace wyth his honourable counſell, in that they go about, to ſet furth the glory of God, in reſtoryng y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the firſt inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucion ſet furth by Chryſt as
<pb facs="tcp:19623:12"/> it apeareth in the ſcriptures, not ſeking te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall poſſeſſyons, which the papiſtes, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row theyr maſſe / haue gotten contrary to the worde of God, in muche greater abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daunce then the ſcriptur permitteth them. The kinges grace I ſay, in ſo doyng, ſhall obteyne no leſſe prayſe for euer, then Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus ſetteth furth of the foreſayd ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, in the latter chapter of his boke: And to the contrarye all they that murmer or grudge agaynſt his maieſties procedinges, without doubt God ſhall confounde them, as he dyd the Ennemies of Dauid / Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Ioſias with many other. I pray you, what a goodly prayſe ſetteth Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticus forth in his. 44. chapter of Ioſias, Sayth he not the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of Ioſias is lyke as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apothecary maketh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny precious ſweteſmellyng thinges toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce ſhalbe ſwete as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in all monethes, &amp; as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> playing of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyke by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wyne? he was appoynted to tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the people agayne and to take away all abhominacions of the vngodly. He derec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted his harte vnto the lord and in the time of the vngodly he ſet vp the worſhyppe of GOD agayne. All Kynges excepte Dauid, Ezechias and Ioſias co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes:
<pb facs="tcp:19623:13"/> for euen the kinges of Iuda alſo forſoke the law of God. Oh God, I wold the papiſtes wolde remembre this ſaying: and ſearch whether the Chryſtian kynges haue forſaken the lawes of God or not. I dare wel wryte, that they can not deny, but that they haue. Wherefore if ſuch to whom the kinges maieſtie and his honorable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſell ſhall commyt the reformatyon of hys graces procedynges, agaynſt the abuſes of Gods word, do ſeke the worlds ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces vnder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pretence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g furth of Gods word / not caring, ſo they get ſubſtaunce wh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of Gods word, as partlye hath apeared in theſe our dayes, both in the cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gy and alſo in the laytye. It wylbe a ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> der to oure Relygion in thoſe dayes as it was euen in the Primatiue churche, as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth in the ſeuenth boke, the .xvij. chapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Euſebius eccleſiaſticall hiſtory, of Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Samoſatenus a byſſhop of Antioch / of whom is ſaid, yf we ſpeake of his pride / it was Intollerable: For he ſhewed hym ſelfe more lyke a captayne then a byſſhop, for ſo much as in going by the ſtreates, he vſed a maruelouſe pryde, in reading the let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters which were ſent hym: before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / naming the anſweares to hys ſecreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries
<pb facs="tcp:19623:13"/> whych accompanyed hym / hauynge ſo great a nombre of folke which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym: and a great multytude followi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hym, in ſuch maner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they which ſawe hym abhorred, hys pryde, and for the ſame, blamed our Relygion. Oh. GOD / doth not the pryde of the byſſhopes in theſe our dayes, reſemble the ſame Paules pryde? He that lyſteth to rede the forſayd chapter out / ſhall ſee muche. But thankes be vnto the lorde, who hath geuen the ſame power vnto the Kinges Maieſtie in theſe dayes / which he gaue to Aurelyan the emperour in thoſe dayes which was: that he gaue po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer to the metrapolytane and other fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full byſſhopes: to depoſe the ſayde Paule: and ſet an other in hys place: whyche dyd preach the worde of God: and not his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thinkinge: as Paule dyd: as appeareth in the ſayd chapter. Truly / if this pride be not lefte both in the Laytie and alſo in the the Clergyie / God wyll plage the worlde / and that very ſhortlye: for Gods worde is not mans inuencion, but the very wyll and worke of God, as witneſſeth Peter in his ſecond Epyſtle the fyrſt Chapter / ſaying: know fyrſt that no prophetie in the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, is done of any priuate interpretation.
<pb facs="tcp:19623:14"/> For the prophecy was neuer wrought by the wyll of man / but the holy men of God ſpake as they were moued of the holy goſt. And this trade vſed the apoſtles, geuinge credyte to Gods worde both in theyr tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching &amp; alſo in theyr miniſtracion / as wye neſſeth. ſainct Peter in his fyrſt epyſtle the fourth chapter ſaying if any man ſpeake, let him talke as though he ſpake the wordes of God. If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſter, let hym do it as of the habily tie whiche God minyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth vnto him. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> primatiue church ſtode by the ſcripturs as Euſebius in his iij. boke the .x. chapter witneſſeth / ſayinge By the which thinges (ſayth he) it is euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in what reuerence we vſe oure ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the which of ſo long tyme and by ſo many ages as is paſt / was neuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that durſt adde / take away or chaunge any thin ge: but all men of our relygion haue thys ſtedfaſt fayth / and beleue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of God, &amp; ſtande to this boke, &amp; for to defende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / if nede require, wil wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly loſe theyr lyues. He ſayth not they wyll make inſurrections and ſtyrre the pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple againſt their prince, as the papiſts haue done theſe. 1200 yeres / for the maintenaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of theyr fayned tradicions &amp; auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes:
<pb facs="tcp:19623:14"/> thys is the very nature of all tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe which mainteyne vn wrytten <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erityes. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of gods peple is not of this ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, but their nature is, to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fautes of prices &amp; of their ſubiectes, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> they ſet led co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the ſcriptures / &amp; gently ſhewe the plages ſet furth in the ſcrypture / for diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being Gods worde, &amp; rather to ſuffre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath, then to ſeke the diſpleaſure or deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theyr prynces, &amp; rather vſe paules trade in theyr preachyng. 1. Cor. xv. ſaying I delyuered vnto you that whych I alſo receaued, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chryſt dyed for our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes according to the ſcripturs, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was buryed / &amp; that he roſe agayne the .iij. day. Paul ſayth not, I delyuered vnto you our au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient fathers cuſtumes / nor yet their ſay ned &amp; inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ceremonies w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> had ſtande ſo many .C. yeres. But he ſaith he delyuered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> he receaued, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> was, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chryſt dyed for our ſynnes according to the ſcriptures &amp; therfore ſayth paul. Gal. 1. Though we our ſelues (ſaith he) or an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preach any other goſpell to you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yt ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue receaued, holde hiaccurſed. O mercifull God, what ſhall we ſay to thoſe, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the popyſh maſſe and ceremonies in the whiche is not declared one Tytle, Howe
<pb facs="tcp:19623:15"/> Chryſt dyed for our ſinnes / according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcripturs? For truly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chatholyke fathers abhorred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: euen in the primatiue church. As hereafter thou mayſt perceaue. And fyrſt Caſtus byſſhoppe ſayth in his .v. bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. He the which preſumeth to follow the cuſtume in contempnyng the veritie / eyther he is enuyous and malycious agaynſt his brethern to whome the verytie is opened, or els he is vnthankfull to God, by whoſe inſpiration his church is inſtructed. Alſo Ciprian ad Pompeium, agaynſt Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Epyſtle, ſayth. The cuſtume which is ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſom, ought not to let the verytie to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue leſſe place, to rhintent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the veritie ſhulde not vanquiſh. For cuſtum without verite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is auncientnes of errour. Wherfore in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, the errour, let vs follow the veritie. Alſo Auſten in his .iij. boke of Baptyſme, the .ix. chapter. And are alſo the wordes of Honoratus Attuca, ſayinge: ſeying Chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte is the veritie / we ought rather to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the veritie then the cuſtume. Alſo Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix Byſſhop ſayth: let none ſet the cuſtume before the veritie, for reaſon &amp; veritie wyll alwayes put furth cuſtume. Alſo. ſ. Cipri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ad Cecilium in hys ſeconde Booke the thyrde Chapter / ſayeth. If ye doo that
<pb facs="tcp:19623:15"/> whiche I commaunce you / from henſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth wyll I not call you ſeruauntes, but frendes. Yea / and that Chryſt ought only to be heard, the father witneſſeth from hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, ſaying: This is my welbeloued ſonne in whom I delyte, heare him. Wherfore if it be ſo that Chriſt ought only to be heard, we ought not to care what thing any befor vs hath eſtemed to be good / but thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which Chryſt teacheth / who was befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re all other. Neyther muſt we follow ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes cuſtume but the veritie of God. For the lorde ſayd by Eſay the prophet. They honour me without cauſe / and teache the commaundementes and doctryne of men. And alſo in the Goſpell, why do ye tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the commaundementes of God, to ſtablyſh your owne tradicions? Wherfore (dere brethern) if anye one of our predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſours, through ignoraunce or ſymplycitie: haue not obſerued and kept that which the lord hath taught vs to do, eyther by exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple or doctryne, it may be reputed to ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, and may be forgeuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> indulgence of the lorde. But it may not be forgeuen vs which now are inſtructed of the lorde: but it is expedient for vs to ſend letters to our companions, that the lordes
<pb facs="tcp:19623:16"/> goſpel &amp; his doctrine be kept ouer al, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wè w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw vs not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> chryſt hath taught &amp; done. Here ye ſe how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> catholik fathers are againſt mannes doctryne and auncient cuſtume / Whoſe doctryne is conformable wyth the apoſtles doctryne, as peter wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in hys ſecond Epyſtell the .iij. Chapt. Remembre the woordes whych were tol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de before of the holy Prophetes, and alſo the commaundementes of vs that be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of the Lorde and ſauyour. Trulye we haue not in the ſcryptures that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment to ſet furth the maſſe or any ſuche Ceremonie as hath bene, and as ſome are yet in the church, for the Apoſtles had ſuffred before any cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was receued into the church, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth al auncient Chronicles. For it was Cix. yeares after chriſts incarnation, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Alexander made the fyrſt holy water. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ll out the yere .cxxix. Telphorus made the lent. About y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of .ijc. xiiij. Cepherinus made or ordeyned a chalyce of glaſſe &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the fyrſte Sacrifyce. About .ijc. lxx. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix ordeyned the hallowynge of the aulters About. ij. clxxxi. Caius ordryned the prye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſhauen ordres. About the yeare of iij. c. xiij. Sylueſter ordeyned creame and oyle to be hallowed of byſſhops. About an
<pb facs="tcp:19623:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. iiij. c. xix. ſoſynus ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halowig of the font on Eaſter euen, and the paſchal taper. About anno .iiij. c. xiij. Mamercus byſſhop of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna ordeyned gang weke. About a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no v. c. xxiii. Felix y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiij. ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anealing of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſycke. About the yere .v. c iiij. Pelagius ordeyned maſſe of requiem, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. about an. vi. c. xxij. Benitacius the .v. ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churchyardes to be ſanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuary. About the yere of .vij. c. xxxij. Grigo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry the .iij. ſet vp Images / cauſing the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to honour them / contrary to a counſell holden in Conſtantinople by Leo the .iiij. Emperour with .iij. c. and .xxx. byſſhops. In the whych counſell Images were con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned and burned, yea euen the very pic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of Chryſt. About the yeare .vij. c. iij. Steuen the .iij. cauſed him ſelf to be born on mens ſhulders. About the yeare of .vij. c. lx. Paulus ordeyned church halowyng. About the yeare. M. lxxiij. Gregorye the vij. ordeyned that prieſtes ſhulde kepe no wyues nor concubines / and for badde to ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te fleſh on the ſatterdayes. Aboute anno. M. lxxxvij. Urbanus the .ij. ordeyned ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>communication. About anno. M. c. xcviij. Innocencius the iij ordeyned anticular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion / to bring in holy belles holy palme, BEADES and Aſſhes wyth all other
<pb facs="tcp:19623:17"/> rayned fantaſies which (as before is ſayd) ye haue not in the teſtament any ſuch doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſet forth by Chryſte nor none of hys apoſtles. Wherfore doctour ſmyth and all thoſe which wryte or preache theis vnwry ten verities to be receaued by the tradicion of the apoſtles, do bely Chryſt and his apo ſtles. For the apoſtles had ſuffred and we reall dead almoſt .xx. yeres before the fyrſt ceremony was inuented, as ye herein may perceaue. Wherfore Paule foreſeing (by the ſpirite of prophetie) that ſuch falſe and erronious doctrine ſhulde com, geuith war ning vnto Timo. in the .iiij. chapter of hys fyrſt Epyſtle / ſaying / The ſpyrite ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth euidently / that in the latter dayes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſhall departe from the fayth / and ſhall geue hede vnto ſpirites of errour and deue lyſh doctryne of them whych ſpeake falſe thorow Ipocriſy, &amp; haue theyr conſciences marked with an whote Iron
/ forbidding to mary, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d commaunding to abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Meates whiche GOD hathe created to be receaued with geuing thankes. Yea and Paule to the Gallath. ſayth. as I ſayde before, ſo ſay I now agayne / if any manne preache vnto you any other thing then that ye haue receaued / holde himac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.
<pb facs="tcp:19623:17"/> Wherfore (this ſaying conſydered) no manne can gather by Paules doctryne but that althoſe ceremonies before recited, were neuer receaued of Paule nor yet of none of the apoſtles. By the which it follo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth that all thoſe which preach theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies to the peple are accurſed by Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le: for ſo much as they were not receaued when Paule preached the curſe. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re let vs repent and beleue Gods wordes ſeing it hath pleaſed him to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it vnto vs, in theſe our days. For if it had bene ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyfully opened vnto our forefathers: the byſſhops of Rome a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theyr maynteyners could neuer haue preuayled agaynſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten princes as they haue done, neyther yet maynteyned their inuented ceremonyes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the which the catholyk fathers wro te: euen when they were inuented as here in apeareth. For Euſebius wrote aboute anno .c. lxix. Origen a about .ii. c. xxv. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian about .ij. c. lix. Chriſoſtom about. iiij c. xiij. Ierome about .iiij. c. xxix. Auſten a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aboute .iilj. c. xxx vij. Theſe men with dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other haue written agaynſt their tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicions / euery one in his tyme / as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in their workes. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citaſion why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcripturs &amp; theſe catholyke me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s workes
<pb facs="tcp:19623:18"/> myght not take place / was for lacke of the prynt. For in the primatiue church, and vn to ſuch time that God had ſent the prynt / it was a greate thing for a man to wryte a byble, yea / aſ much as a man myght to in his whole life. Wherfor for lacke of gods woorde, the people myght nor come to the knowledge of the biſhop of Romes deue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh inuencion. Yea, and we may be ſure in caſe the ſcriptures had been as plentyfull and as leful to euery man / in the primatiue church / as they are now in theſe our days / the a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tichriſtes of Rome &amp; all their ayders ſhuld haue had as much to do in the ſetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as men haue now in the pulling downe of them. For the holy Scriptures were then in few mens handes ſo that the Chriſtians had not to ſtabliſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in Chriſt, but only by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers. And after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> apoſtles &amp; ſincere pachers, were depar ted to god / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Romiſh biſſhops to ſtabliſh their earthly kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to become lords of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole chriſten relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as well ouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prices as ouer their ſubiectes, as it may apeare by aunciant chronicles. For in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .x. boke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vi. chap of Euſebius works it is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned, howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> counſell of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtatine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great, waſt
<pb facs="tcp:19623:18"/> decreed that the auncient cuſtumes ſhulde be kept in Alexandria &amp; in the citie of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: to wyt, that the byſſhop of Alexandria ſhulde haue the charge of the churches in Egypt: and he in Rome, of the churches in Rome and about Rome. Now, this Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten counſell being kept .iiij. c. yeares after Chryſt / coulde not fynde the Romiſh byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Chriſtes ſucceſſour / but only ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches of Rome &amp; about rome. I pray you from whence cam hys auctoritie ſence to be called Chryſtes ſucceſſoure ouer the whole chriſten congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? yf it had com from Chriſt, this counſell (no doubt) wold haue found it. Truly I can not gather of whome he receaued it, onles be receaued it of that deuell that wolde haue had Chryſt to fall downe and honour him / as is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Mathew .iiij. but Chriſt had him avoy de, but I thinke Sylueſter ſent for him a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d receaued that which Chryſt refuſed / and it maye well appeare to be from thence. For ſence the ſame pope ſylueſter receaued the poſſeſſions, which was almoſt .iiij. c. yeres after CHRIST, he &amp; his ſucceſſours for the moſt part haue euer ſence perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the trewe CHRYSTYANES
<pb facs="tcp:19623:19"/> and that ye may perceaue the ſetting furth of the ſcryptures in thoſe dayes was not for euery man / by the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſo char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geable. But it was onely a prynces worke as Chrodoryke biſſhop of Cirocopolis in the fyrſt booke of hys ſtory the .xvi. chapter maketh mencion of an Epyſtle ſent by the forſayde conſtantine to Euſehuis, the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour wherof is this. It hath ſemed vs go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>od to ſygnyfye vnto the, that thou prepare L. volumes of the ſcryptures, and pryneye pally thoſe the which thou knoweſte to be neceſſary to the inſtitucion, doctryne and vſage which hath been accuſtumed to be ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to the churches, and let them be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in good Parchement and well trined by good worckmen, hauing good knowledge in the acte of the ſcryptures. And we alſo haue ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t letters to our general geuernoue of the prouinces, to take charge and dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tly to miniſter al thynges neceſſary / to the reſtoring of the ſame volumes, and it to be thy worke and dilygently to enforce thy ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe that the ſame volumes maye be ſhortly ready and appareylled as it apperteyneth. And further by the aucthorytie of our let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Sealed by vs, ſent to the we giue the power to take and vſe openly .ij. Charets
<pb facs="tcp:19623:19"/> or cartes to cauſe the ſayd volumes dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be conueyed to the citie of conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinople. Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle reader / here may ye ſe what paynes and charges it was to thys noble Emperour to ſet furth the ſcryptures, in thoſe dayes. Iohn Caryon ſayth in the. 3. boke of hys chronicle that thys conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cauſed the newe Teſtament to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed before him for a wytnes of hys ſaith I praye you wherfore dyd conſtantine ſet furth theſe ſcryptures. Truly becauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wicked Dyocleſyan the. xxxv. Emperour in the .ix. yeare of hys reygne / which was about the yeare of Chryſt. 288. as Cation wrytteth / dyd as appeareth in the ſeuently boke the ſecond chapter of Euſebius ſtory cauſe thys proclamacyon followyng / to be proclaymed, which was that the churches of the chriſtyans whiche myght be founde ſhuld be ouerthrowen to the fondacions &amp; the bokes and ſcryptures burned, and that all thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> relygyon, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> had any dignitie or office, ſhuld be put forth &amp; remaine aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe ſlaues which perſeuered in the chryſten fayth myght not obtayne ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bertie, the occaſyon herof was, that the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retyke Manicheus, had fowen diſſention amonge the chryſtians. O Lorde haue we not had thy ſcrypturs brent in curdayes?
<pb facs="tcp:19623:20"/> Yf we aſke wyncheſter and London / they wyll laye, yea: yea, and ſo ſay I to: But ye may beleue me, I was very heauye whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I heard of it. yea / and as heauye as they are now ſory that they be printed agayne. But thankes be to the lorde, our kinges maieſteacute; may go farther wyth hundreth pounde in printing, then conſtantine might haue done wyth thre thouſand pounde in wrytynge. For the lacke of bokes cauſed the byſſhops of Rome and his ayders to preuayle in all counſels ſence the fyrſt: Yea and in all the xxiij. ſciſmes paſt / to rule all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges as they wolde, and to make what they wolde, and diſcalow what they wolde. But in this, the xxiiii. ſciſme or deuiſion I truſt the byſſho pe of Rome and all his Papiſtes ſhall be ouerthrowen through y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> word of GOD, which by the prynt is abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly ſpredde abrode in all Chryſtendome. A worke which God neuer opened to man, ſence the worlde began tyll the yeare of Chryſt. M iiii. c. lii. which in that yere was opened to one called Iohannes fauſtius in the Cytie of Magunce or menth in Germany.</p>
               <p>Wherfore let vs giue god tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes &amp; reioyce that he hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs, in theſe our dayes, that ſcience wherby al thoſe that loue the lyght
<pb facs="tcp:19623:20"/> maye haue the ſame, for alytle charges / I meane the worde of God who is the Auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of lyght. By whoſe lyght, the kyngs maieſtye with hys honorable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel goeth about to ouerthrowe the Popes maſtres Miſſa, the ſucceſſour of the Iſraelytes / ne huſthan. Wherfor / let vs daily pray to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lorde the Aucthour of the canonicall ſcryptures / that he wyll pro ſper the Kinges maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with my Lorde protectour and his hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell / in the ſetting furth of his worde: So that through hys helpe, they may ouercome the ennemies of the ſame hys worde and of his graces royalmes and dominions, Amen.</p>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
